[Music]
Stanford
University well I think what I'm going
to
do
is take roughly a half an hour or
something like
that and just discuss some elementary
mathematics now I want you to learn this
mathematics and if need be to look it up
it's three simple
pieces three simple pieces of
mathematics all elementary and I suspect
most of you either know this or knew it
at one time but it's so Central that I
think we need to lay it out and uh and
use
it use it lay it out for few future
purposes okay the first piece of
mathematics is called lrange multiply
how many people here have seen lrange
multipliers how many of those people
remember what a lrange multiplier
is so roughly half the people have seen
it can use it would that be fair to say
how many people have never seen a lrange
multiplier or can't remember what it
is all right so uh the the answer is the
majority of you have but uh I'm going to
remind you anyway because it is
absolutely Central we're constantly
minimizing or maximizing things subject
to constraints what is the thing that
we're likely to minimize incidentally or
maximize sorry entropy but we'll get to
why entropy
uh not tonight next time I suspect but
um why we maximize entropy but yes
thermal equilibrium is a state of
Maximum entropy and that means we want
to Max maximize something as a function
of something else we want to maximize a
certain function as a function of the
variables that Define it number one
number two there are
constraints we don't just want to M
maximize a function but we want to
maximize a function subject to some
constraints what might the constraints
be well a particular con straint might
be that we know the total energy of the
system or we know the average energy of
the system for some reason we may know
the average energy of the system for
example we might
have
again a container full of a lot of
molecules we break it up into small
pieces we're going to study one small
piece and I tell you that the total
energy in that container is what
whatever it is 20 zillion
um uh
Jews okay I also tell you that it's
composed of a bunch of identical Parts
how many identical Parts 10,000 of them
what's the average energy in each one
well you take the total energy and you
divide it by the number of parts and
that tells you the the to the average
energy in each part now I want to focus
on this
part and say I know the average energy
and I want to maximize the entropy
subject to the constraint that the total
energy is
fixed that's a problem that's the kind
of problem that emerges time and time
again over and over another example is
we may to know the total amount of
electric charge in a in a region and we
may want to maximize the entropy given
the total amount of electric charge or
the total amount of angular momentum or
whatever so we constantly face problems
of minimizing or maximizing the
mathematical uh subject of minimizing
and maximizing are equivalent to each
other or the same uh we constantly want
to maximize
functions of several
variables subject to constraints on
those variables what does that mean
example a function of two
variables let's let's literally take an
example uh I want to minimize minimize
or maximize minimize I think
X2 +
y^2 now anybody can minimize X2 + y^2
what's the minimum value of X2 + y^2
it can't be less than Z because x^2 and
y^2 are both positive at x equal 0 and Y
equals 0 it is equal to 0 but it's not
equal to zero anywhere else so the
minimum is right at xal y equals z and
the function is equal to zero at that
point but now supposing I tell you I
want to minimize it subject to a
constraint I want to know where X2 + y
squ is minimum
given that I don't know let's say x + 2
y is equal to uh to
one right to draw
picture we can plot on the plane here
the Contours of X2 + y^2 X2 + y^2 the
cont like a contour
map right at the center it's minimized
and as we move away it forms a bowl uh a
Valley and the contour map would look
like this
on the other hand and of course the
minimum of the function is right at the
center on the other hand I won't really
want to minimize it subject to a
constraint and that constraint is uh x +
2 y = 1 that's a straight line and I
don't know it's a straight line maybe it
looks something like that so what I'm
really asking is where along this line
is x^2 +
y^2
minimized given that you're on line well
that's certainly not at the origin here
it's somewhere along here looks like
it's about over here doesn't
it X2 + y^2 of course is just the the
squar distance from the origin and so
you're kind of asking along this line
where is the line closest to the origin
that's the geometric problem that
corresponds to it but the mathematics
problem is to minimize x s + y^2 subject
to a constraint that x x + 2 y is equal
to 1 how do you do that well
uh one way would just be to eliminate
let's do it we could eliminate one of
the variables plug it into here and then
minimize the remaining function for
example what does that mean we could
solve for x and find that X is equal to
1 - 2
Y and then plug it into here and we
would have 1 - 2
y^ 2ar that's x^2 +
y^2 let's just call this f f on the line
on the red line F would be given by this
and then the next step is just to
minimize f with respect to Y we don't
have to worry about the constraint
anymore because we've already taken the
constraint into account so that's one
way of doing the problem now in many
cases the constraint is just too
complicated to solve it might be some
stupid complicated function that's just
too complicated to solve but there is
another way to do the problem and the
problem is called the method of lrange
multipliers um maybe I'll perhaps as we
go along I will prove that it
works uh for a simple for well not for
this example but maybe a little more
General example but let me just tell you
what the method is I'm going to tell you
the rule then we can try to see maybe
why the rule is
true all right what you do here's our
problem we have a function of some
variables in this case just
two function of X and
Y and we want to minimize it given that
some other function G of X and
[Music]
Y is equal to zero g of X and Y in this
case over here just corresponds to what
was it uh x + 2 y y - 1 x + 2 y - 1 is
equal to
0 that's the
constraint all right here's the trick
that you do you take the constraint and
you multiply it by a new variable the
new variable is often called
Lambda usually a Greek letter and it's
called a lrange
multiplier you add that to F add or
subtract it doesn't matter
uh you add it to F and now you have a
new function of X and Y that also
depends on this auxiliary variable which
we're going to get rid of soon
enough we're going to get rid of it in a
moment uh but we have a new
[Music]
thing which is f and Lambda G and then
what we do is we just
minimize f plus Lambda G with respect to
X and Y ignoring the
constraint for get the constraint and
just think of this new object here and
minimize it with respect to X and Y okay
how do you minimize a function of two
variables with respect to uh with
respect to its
variables you differentiate with respect
to the variables and you set the result
equal to zero so that would
say we differentiate DF by
DX plus Lambda Lambda is treated as just
a constant times DG by
DX and we set that equal to zero that's
one equation and the other equation is
DF by
Dy plus Lambda DG by
Dy is equal to zero those are the two
equations for minimizing this particular
object over here
here all right here are two equations
for two unknowns X and Y both of them
depend on X and
Y X and Y X and
Y and we can solve them for X and Y but
wait a minute we have this thing Lambda
there what do we do with that thing
Lambda right the answer for X and Y will
depend on this parameter
Lambda what we do with the parameter
Lambda at the
end after we have solved this problem
over here implicitly in terms of Lambda
is that we set Lambda to whatever value
was necessary in order that the
constraint the original constraint g
equals z is really satisfied I'm going
to give you an example I'm going to show
you how it works by
example in fact we might as well do that
example and then I'm going to show you
why it works show you that it work show
you how it works and then why it
works okay incidentally you could
imagine having more variables XY z w and
have several
constraints I'll tell you later on what
you do with several constraints but
let's just do it as a function of two
variables for one constraint okay so
let's solve this problem up here here's
our
problem minimize x^2 +
y^2 subject to the constraint that x + 2
y - 1 is equal to
0 well
we add this quantity x^2 +
y^2 plus
Lambda time the
constraint x + 2 y - 1 in this case the
one is not going to be very important to
this calculation that's a new object and
now we minimize it how do we minimize it
we differentiate it with respect to X
and set the result equal to zero what's
the derivative of this that's
2x plus Lambda x = 0 we differentiate
with respect to
lamb oh sorry plus Lambda good thank
you plus Lambda equal 0 2x plus Lambda
equal 0 and then same thing with Y 2 Y
and in this case it's + 2 Lambda extra
two here equals
z now we can solve for x and y in terms
of Lambda we don't know what Lambda is
yet but let's solve it in terms of X and
Y uh let's solve for x and y in terms of
Lambda X is equal to minus Lambda / 2
that's this equation x is minus Lambda /
2 and Y I think is just equal to minus
Lambda
everybody agree with that right okay so
we've solved that problem except we
don't know what Lambda is what we do now
is we choose Lambda so that the
constraint is actually satisfied let's
do
that x + 2 y - 1 is equal to 0 let's
plug in the solution the solution is X
which is minus Lambda / 2 this one plus
2 y which is minus 2 Lambda I
believe 2 Y is - 2
Lambda minus
one is equal to zero sorry is equal to 1
is equal to one I just transposed the
one over to the other side and now what
does that mean in terms of
Lambda excuse me
2 is 4 over
two
uh okay so this is what minus 5 Lambda -
5 Lambda equal 1 or Lambda is equal to -
fths and now we solve our problem Lambda
is equal to - 25s which means Lambda / 2
is lookus Lambda / 2 is
1/5 I think let's see Lambda over
2 yeah is 1/5 and Y is equal
to 2
fths I've just plugged in what Lambda
is minus Lambda is 2 fsus Lambda / 2 is
1/5 and we have now found out where
this curve or where this
line achieves its closest distance to
the origin that was the mathematics
problem minimize x^2 + y^2 which is just
the square of the distance of a point to
the origin minimize it along this line
and that means find the point along the
line which is closest to the
center
right now we could check in we can check
independently of course we could do the
calculation the other way by
eliminating the constraint by solving
the constraint for one of the variables
and plugging it back in and we could uh
we could do it that way of course we'll
get the same
answer let me show you why this works so
just a little bit of algebra it just
takes a little bit of algebra to see why
it works and it's very general it's
extremely General it's
not uh X2 + y^2 was just an arbitrary
function that I picked
any other
function the fact that I chose the
constraint to be a straight line a
linear function again nothing special
about that okay let's uh let's do the
problem not this problem but a general
problem in both ways and see that we get
the same
answer so let's start by the method of
eliminating one of the variables from
the constraint here we here's our
problem we have f of x and
y we want to minimize it subject to the
constraint that g of X and Y is equal to
Zer G of X and Y equals 0 is some curve
and it means we're minimizing F along
that
curve all right here's the way I'm going
to do it I'm going to imagine this it
may be too hard to do but it doesn't
matter all I have to do is Imagine doing
it solving this equation for one of the
two variables which one all right let's
imagine solving for y if we solve this
equation for y it will tell us what Y is
as a function of
X in other words this was some
curve it corresponds to a curve that
represents y as a function of X let's
not worry right now whether it's single
valued not single valued that that
that's not an important issue here it
gives us a y as a function of X then we
plug that back into here and when we say
what we're really trying to minimize is
f
ofx and Y
ofx this is now a function of a single
variable it's only a function of X
because Y is now a definite function of
x f ofx and Y becomes F ofx and Y ofx
okay next step what's the next
step differentiate this with respect to
X and set the result equal to
zero that will find us the minimum of X
subject to the constraint so let's see
let's do
that we have to differentiate the X
dependence that's DF by
DX but then we have to add to that the
derivative of f with respect to
[Music]
Y time D time Dy by DX this is an
ordinary
derivative Dy by DX
DX all right this is the change in F
when we change the first argument here
of the function and this is the change
due to the change in y but the change in
y is determined by the change in X okay
and we set this equal to
zero okay that's that's an equation but
what about d y by DX what do I know
about Dy by DX let's see what we can
figure out about Dy by DX this curve
here is a curve of constant G let's
imagine moving along it imagine moving
along it and making a small differential
displacement a small differential
displacement along the curve of constant
G will not change G by definition if
we're moving along the curve of constant
G then G doesn't change so I can write
the following equation along this curve
the derivative of G with respect to x
times
DX plus the derivative of G with respect
to
Y time d y is equal to zero that says G
doesn't change when I make a small
differential displacement the reason I
did this is because this allows me to
Sol solve for Dy by DX in terms of
things involving the constraint G all
right so Dy by DX we just divide by
DX and what do we get we get Dy by
DX d y by
DX is equal to
minus D G by
DX divided
by D G by Dy
right very simple we just use the
statement that the constraint along the
constraint G is constant and that tells
us something about the derivative of y
with respect to X along that curve and
now we plug it in we plug it into
here let's see what we get Dy by DX well
might as well write it over we get DF by
DX
X now there's going to be a minus sign
from the Dy by DX so let's put the minus
sign here DF by
Dy and now d y by DX except I already
took into account the minus sign this is
D G by
DX divided by DG by
Dy let's put it in there DG by
Dy equals z let's multiply by DG by Dy y
so we get D G by d
y equals
z that's not a badl looking
equation that's the
equation after we've
eliminated y this is the equation which
solves for the minimum of f subject to G
what I want to show you I don't want you
to use this this is not we're not going
to use this well we're going to do is
show that you get exactly the same
relationship from the method of lrange
multipliers okay so let's go to the
method of lrange
multipliers here are the two
equations that followed from the method
of lrange multipliers but now let's
eliminate Lambda from the equation how
can we do that we can solve for Lambda
in one equation and plug it into the
other all right so let's see we have
here
Lambda it says Lambda is equal to
minus DF by
DX ided by DG by DX is that
right let's see yeah minus because I've
got the transpose and then Lambda will
be DF by DX / by DG by DX now let's plug
it into
here right let's plug Lambda into here
so we have
Lambda minus
s DF by
DX divided by DG by DX but instead of
dividing by DG by DX over here let's
just multiply by DG by DX over
here all right the really was divided by
DG by DX but then I just multiply the
right hand side is zero okay hopefully
it's the same
equation I'm not even going to look
I I I hope it's the same equation is it
the same
equation they both have minus
sign
H they're both
[Music]
zero right we have to multiply by minus
one to get them to be the same but they
are the same all right so this was just
a simple
illustration that the method of there's
an intuitive geometric picture of it but
uh it it takes longer to explain than
just to do the
arithmetic the method of lrange
multipliers is completely equivalent to
solving the
constraint and then plugging back in and
it's usually easier okay so what are the
rules again you take the constraint you
multiply it by Lambda you add it to the
thing that you're trying to make minimum
or maximum you then differentiate as if
you were trying to minimize the whole
thing you get two equations let's
say or however many equations there are
variables in the problem
doesn't have to be two okay so the other
one is DF by
Dy plus Lambda DG by
Dy equal
[Music]
Z you solve those two equations they're
two equations for two unknowns X and Y
but then after you
finished you choose Lambda so that the
constraint is actually satisfied
so that the constraint g equals 0 is
satisfied so I gave you some examp an
example make up your own examples work
out uh I don't know instead of X2 + y^2
uh take um X Cub + y cubed and the
constraint is that s of x + y is three I
don't know no s of X Plus y can't be
three e to x + y is equal to
3 right all right just make up an
example or two
try doing it by by eliminating one of
the variables and you'll quickly
discover that it's usually easier to
just use the method of lrange
multipliers but one of the nice things
about the method of lrange multipliers
it doesn't force you to single out one
of the
variables for special
treatment the method of that I used here
singled out
X as opposed to y
it wasn't special but I singled it out
to solve for it I I solve for y actually
and so I didn't treat the variables
symmetrically no problem there's nothing
wrong with that but it's a nice feature
of the method of lrange multipliers that
it treats the variables
symmetrically uh let me just tell you
without proving supposing I had a
function of several
variables function of X1 dot dot dot dot
xn whatever they happen to
be and now I have a collection of
constraints not just one constraint for
example I may have two constraints one
of the constraints might be that the
total energy is fixed another constraint
might be that the total charge is fixed
or the energy and the angular momentum
they would be two separate
constraints and so I would have a set of
constraints G1 let's call it is equal to
zero G1 is a function of the same set of
variables G2 is equal to zero however
many I have it's important that there
not be more constraints than variables
otherwise you can't solve
it if you have more constraints than
variables in general there is no
solution but uh but fewer constraints
than variables then what you do is you
introduce a lrange multiplier for each
of the constraints so you write
f plus the first lrange multiplier time
G1 plus the second lrange multiplier
time G2 and however many lrange
multipliers you have or however many
constraints you have and then you
minimize or
differentiate the result with respect to
the X's set them equal to
zero the f plus the sum of Lambda I
GI with respect
to each one of the x's and set it equal
to
[Music]
zero solve
it and
then choose all of the lambdas how many
lambdas do you have one for each
constraint choose all of the lambdas so
that all the constraints are satisfied
that's that's the method of lrange
multipliers and as I said it is Central
to statistical mechanics we will use it
over and over again and if you're not
familiar with it just look it up on U
I'm sure you can find it easily on the
uh just Google it lrange multipliers
it's probably a Wikipedia
article and try it out work with it a
little bit and become amiliar with
it I will not explain it again but I
will use it
again over and
over what is the thing that we're
typically going to minimize the entropy
what are the
constraints constraints such as we know
the total energy we know the total
whatever it happens to
be okay next little theorem these things
are too small to really be called
theorems uh Sterlings approxim
to the factorial function everybody know
what Sterling anybody not know what
Sterling's approximation
is if anybody not
know oh no no no but I mean do you know
how to prove
it
okay where it comes from all right so
let's uh let's just review very quickly
Sterling's
approximation in factorial occurs over
and over in all sorts of probability
contexts every time you calculate
permutations in combinations in order to
calculate
probabilities in factorials appear all
over the place okay
um generally the NS which appear are
very large numbers they have to do with
how many ways there are arranging or
rearranging a large number of variables
in some large number of way ways and so
it's important to have an approximation
of reliable approximation which becomes
better and better as n becomes large for
the factorial
function n
[Music]
factorial equals 1 * 2 * 3 dot dot dot
dot up to
n that's the factorial function
right all right now I want to find a
good estimate for it what I'm going to
begin with is by taking its logarithm
I'm going to Cal I'm going to estimate
the logarithm of n factorial once I've
estimated the logarithm of n factorial
how do I estimate n
factorial we exponentiate the logarithm
right so it's just as good to all right
so let's calculate the let's estimate
the logarithm of n factorial log n
factorial that's equal to log of one
plus log of two plus log of three plus
and so forth and so
on log one log one happens to be zero
but nevertheless write it down plus log
two plus log 3 dot dot dot plus log
in all right so what do I have let's
plot in in this direction
let's plot logarithm of n now what does
the logarithm function look like it
looks like it's zero at n equals 1 and
it looks something like
this and basically what we're doing is
we're adding up the
areas n = 1 n = 2 N = 3 dot dot dot
we're adding up the areas under this
logarithm curve here all right when n
becomes
large it's a good
approximation to the sum to replace it
by the
integral right the
integral so let's consider then instead
of considering the sum here this is sum
of log of n from n = 1 to Nal sorry it's
log of uh let's call it log of
x log of x from x =
1 to X =
N and we're going to replace that
by integral
DX logarithm of
X okay so we have the
problem of integrating logarithm of X
it's easy to do you just look it up in a
table of
[Music]
integrals that incidentally means find a
function whose derivative is logarithm
of X I'll tell you how I would think
about it if I didn't know the answer
I would begin by saying well logarithm
at least for large x is a very slowly
varying function it practically doesn't
vary at all logarithm is a terribly
slowly varying function so I might I
might just try saying well what if this
logarithm were a constant then what
would be the integral DX of a
constant x times the constant right X
time the constant okay so let's try x *
log
X x * log X if log X were a constant and
it's very very slowly varying if we
replaced it by a constant then the right
answer would be x * the constant right
so this shouldn't be too far off now
let's differentiate it and see if we
really get logarithm of X all right so
what's the derivative of x log
X well it's got two factors so the
derivative of the first factor is
1 time the second factor that gives us
good that gives us log X
right but there's another term what's
the other
term it's x times the derivative of
logarithm of X but the derivative of
logarithm of X is 1
/x okay so what do we get + one not log
of x not log X + one but log X 1 + log
X so that's not so good we wanted to get
log X we didn't want to get 1 plus log
X okay but all we have to do now is to
subtract something from this whose
derivative is
one which is
X that my friends is the integral of log
X X log X x - x differentiate it you'll
get X sorry you'll get log X so we now
know that this oh this integral goes
from 1 to
n and the answer
is n log
n minus
n I've just substituted for x I've just
integral from 1 to n one end point just
gives zero the other end point gives n
log n minus n
this is Sterling's approximation for the
logarithm of n
factorial and actually this is the way
we're going to wind up using it n log n
minus n because we're generally going to
be interested in the logarithm of n
factorial but just
to just to uh I know what's going on
just to complete the calculation
we now want to exponentiate it all right
so we want to take e to the N log
in e to the minus n we have the sum or
the difference of two terms when I
exponentiate it I will
get e to the N log n that's e to what's
what's e to the N log
n that's n to the N same as n to the
n n to the n is the same as e to the N
log n * eus
n this is Sterling's
approximation Sterling Sterling's
approximation to the factorial function
it grows very fast n to the N grows very
rapidly but not quite as rapidly as n to
the N it's modulated by a decreasing
function e to the minus n okay so that's
a second little Lemma or theorem that
you must know in order to
do statistical
mechanics and the third
one is a combinatoric fact simple
combinatoric fact but one and once we do
it we won't do it again or we won't uh
we won't explain it again but let's do
it
anyway um I'll tell you what the problem
that we're really interested in
supposing I
have n
copies of the same system now you can
just think of this as n
boxes n
boxes and each box can be in a state the
states of a single box I'll label them
over here they actually correspond to
the energy states of the
system but here they are vertically is
energy this is the I State over
here and each one of these boxes can be
identified with a state in here in other
words each box is in a state or has a
particular State labeled by one of these
eyes we could draw a picture or we could
draw a
figure if the first box happens to be in
this state over here I'll put a line
over there like that if the second box
happens to be in the same state I'll put
another line over
here supposing the third box is in a
different state over here and the fourth
box is in yet a different one over here
and the fifth box let's put a fifth box
in just uh to add one more just happens
to be in the same state as this one over
here all right so a diagram like this
is a description of the states of in
copies there are in copies here of a
system and copies each with its own
State
now here's an interesting
quantity oh what should we label yes we
labeled the states I notice that I does
not stand for which box we're talking
about it stands for the possible state
within a box the possible configuration
within a
box and I'm taking them to be
discreet all right I can ask how many
boxes are
there in the first state this is I
equals 1 how many boxes are there well
in this case there are no boxes with I
equals 1 but in general the answer will
be an integer N Sub one that's the
number of boxes in state number number
one the number of Bo the number of boxes
in state number two is N Sub 2 N Sub
three and so
forth what do these NS have to add up
to I wonder if the lecture is supposed
to be in here
tonight it's supposed to be in the other
room no yeah okay uh
okay what must these ends add up to
begin the number of boxes in the first
state plus the number of boxes in the
second state plus the number of boxes in
the third state and so forth have to add
up to end but the question I want to ask
is how many ways are there of choosing a
state for each box such that there are
N1 boxes in the state one N2 boxes in
the state two n three boxes in the state
three and so forth how many ways are
there of getting a given set of
NS okay anybody know the
answer oh I wrote The Answer down in the
yeah the answer was written in the notes
so you do know the answer I
presume okay uh let me write the answer
down and then if we have time I'll try
to explain why it's the
answer the answer involves a bunch of
factorials and is the primary reason why
uh why I
bothered giving you an approximation for
the factorial function all right the
answer is very simple it's simple but uh
but subtle it's capital N
factorial what should we call this thing
um I think I just called it I don't
remember did I give it a name in the
notes the number of ways of Distributing
a state to each
box such that there are N1 boxes in
state number one N2 boxes in state
number two and so forth and so on uh
I'll just call it
number
[Music]
number it is
equal the capital N
factorial divided by a product and the
product is N1 factorial N2 factorial n 3
factorial dot dot
dot what happens if some of the states
are unoccupied altogether for example
this state over here doesn't appear in
any of these boxes let's call this the
42nd State over here what is N Sub 48
zero that looks a little odd a zero
factorial downstairs but what's zero
factorial one that's a definition of a
factorial
function uh so all of the unoccupied
States just give a bunch of ones 1 * 1 *
1 * 1 is just one so you only get
something interesting from the states
which are actually filled and if there
if there are three boxes in the first
state then there's a three factorial
four boxes in the second state then
there's a four factorial and so forth
all right this is the answer to the
question of how many ways there are of
making a configuration where there's a
given number of boxes in each state
let's see if we can uh let's uh see if
we can at least motivate the
answer I wonder if we should just go in
there and get some seats yeah yeah I
think that's the thing to do
um if we come in a little early next
time I'll finish up the derivation of
this 10 minutes
early uh but you can also look it up
again
Wikipedia for more please visit us at
stanford.edu